Curriculum Vitae

KC Sivaramakrishnan

Computer Laboratory University of Cambridge sk826@cl.cam.ac.uk November 18, 2017

15 JJ Thomson Avenue Cambridge CB3 0FD Tel: +44 79828 42499

Summary

I am interested in the design and implementation of concurrent programming languages targeting scalable platforms such as many-core processors and compute clouds. My research spans programming models, compilers, static analysis, schedulers, threading systems, and memory management.

Education

PhD — Computer Science

May 2011 – Dec 2014

Thesis Title: Functional Programming Abstractions for Weakly Consistent Systems

Purdue University, USA

Advisor: Suresh Jagannathan

Master of Science — Computer Science

Aug 2008 – May 2011
Purdue University, USA

Bachelor of Engineering — Computer Science and Engineering

Aug 2004 – May 2008

PSG College of Technology
Anna University, India

Experience

Senior Research Associate, University of Cambridge

Advisors: Alan Mycroft, Anil Madhavapeddy

Nov 2017 – present Cambridge, UK

Technical director of OCaml Labs leading the development of Multicore OCaml project. Applying programming languages and program verfication to solve extreme-scale parallelism and distribution.

Research Fellow, Royal Commission for the Exhibition of 1851 Oct 2015 – present

Research Fellow, Darwin College, Cambridge Oct 2015 – present

Research Associate, University of Cambridge Dec 2014 – Oct 2017

Research Assistant, Purdue University

Advisor: Suresh Jagannathan

Aug 2008 – Dec 2014 West Lafayette, IN, USA

My research focused on discovering new language abstractions and developing runtime system techniques to ease programming weakly consistent systems. To this end, I have built MultiMLton, a parallel and distributed extension of MLton Standard ML compiler and runtime and Quelea, a shallow extension of Haskell for declarative programming over eventually consistent data stores.

Teaching Assistant, Purdue University

Undergraduate C Programming (CS180) Graduate Programming Languages (CS565) West Lafayette, IN, USA Aug 2012 – Dec 2012

Aug 2011 - Dec 2011

My tasks included designing and evaluating weekly projects, office hours for one-on-one instruction, and grading.

Research Intern, Microsoft Research, Cambridge

Advisors: Tim Harris, Simon Marlow, and Simon Peyton Jones

Feb 2012 – May 2012

Cambridge, UK

I developed a concurrency substrate for Glasgow Haskell Compiler (GHC) to allow programmers to modularly implement user-level schedulers and concurrency libraries for Haskell threads in Haskell, without having to re-engineer critical runtime system components. The concurrency substrate is built around one-shot continuations and uses transactional memory for coordination.

Research Intern, Samsung Information Systems America (R&D)

Advisor: Daniel Waddington

May 2010 – Aug 2010 San Jose, CA, USA

I was part of the core team that developed SNAPPLE programming language – a safe and concurrent extension of C++ targeted at many-core processors. The task involved designing language extensions for concurrency, compiler extensions for safety, and a runtime for executing large number of lightweight threads. SNAPPLE was implemented as a veneer on top of C++ using LLNL Rose source-to-source compiler.

Intern, Advanced Numerical Research and Analysis Group

Dec 2007 – Apr 2008

Advisor: Sankar Chnab

Hyderabad, India

As a part of the Compiler Engineering group, I ported Kaffe, an open source Java VM to an embedded microprocessor ANUPAMA and a desktop processor ABACUS. Developed a lightweight threading subsystem, and implemented a JIT backed for ABACUS.

Journal Publications

Concurrent System Programming with Effect Handlers

Nov 2017

J6 Stephen Dolan, Spiros Eliopolous, Daniel Hillerstrm, Anil Madhavapeddy, KC Sivaramakrishnan, Leo White

J5

J3

J1

Post-proceedings of the Symposium on Trends in Functional Programming (TFP) (accepted)

Eff directly in OCaml

Oct 2017

Oleg, Kiselyov, KC Sivaramakrishnan

Post-proceedings of the ML Workshop (accepted)

Composable Scheduler Activations for Haskell

Jun 2016

J4 KC Sivaramakrishnan, Tim Harris, Simon Marlow, Simon Peyton Jones Journal of Functional Programming (JFP)

Representation without Taxation: A Uniform, Low-Overhead, and High-Level Interface to Eventu-

Mar 2016

ally Consistent Key-Value Stores
KC Sivaramakrishnan, Gowtham Kaki, Suresh Jagannathan

IEEE Data Engineering Bulletin, 39(1): 52 – 64

MultiMLton: A Multicore-aware Runtime for Standard ML

Nov 2014

J2 KC Sivaramakrishnan, Lukasz Ziarek, Suresh Jagannathan Journal of Functional Programming (JFP), 24(6): 613 – 674

bournat of Lancetonat Programming (b11), 27(0). 010

Feb 2013

KC Sivaramakrishnan, Mohammad Qudeisat, Lukasz Ziarek, Karthik Nagaraj, Patrick Eugster *Science of Computer Programming (SCP)*, 78(2): 147 – 167

Invited paper

Efficient Sessions

Conference Publications

Continuation Passing Style for Effect Handlers

Sep 2017

C9 Daniel Hillerstrm, Sam Lindley, Robert Atkey, KC Sivaramakrishnan

International Conference on Formal Structures for Computation and Deduction (FSCD)

DaLi: Database as a Library

May 2017

Gowtham Kaki, KC Sivaramakrishnan, Thomas Gazagnaire, Anil Madhavapeddy, Suresh Jagannathan The 2nd Summit on Advances in Programming Languages (SNAPL)

Oral Presentation

Declarative Programming over Eventually Consistent Data Stores

Jun 2015

C7 KC Sivaramakrishnan, Gowtham Kaki, Suresh Jagannathan

International Conference on Programming Language Design and Implementation (PLDI)

Rx-CML: A Prescription for Safely Relaxing Synchrony

Jan 2014

C6 KC Sivaramakrishnan, Lukasz Ziarek, Suresh Jagannathan

Symposium on Practical Aspects of Declarative Languages (PADL)

C5	A Coherent and Managed Runtime for ML on the SCC KC Sivaramakrishnan, Lukasz Ziarek, Suresh Jagannathan Many-core Architecture Research Community Symposium (MARC) Best paper award	Nov 2012	
C4	Eliminating Read Barriers through Procrastination and Cleanliness KC Sivaramakrishnan, Lukasz Ziarek, Suresh Jagannathan International Symposium on Memory Management (ISMM)	Jun 2012	
C3	Composable Asynchronous Events Lukasz Ziarek, KC Sivaramakrishnan, Suresh Jagannathan International Conference on Programming Language Design and Implementation (PLDI)	Jun 2011	
C2	Efficient Session Type Guided Distributed Interaction KC Sivaramakrishnan, Karthik Nagaraj, Lukasz Ziarek, Patrick Eugster International Conference on Coordination Models and Languages (COORDINATION)	June 2010	
C1	Partial Memoization of Concurrency and Communication Lukasz Ziarek, KC Sivaramakrishnan, Suresh Jagannathan International Conference on Functional Programming (ICFP)	Sep 2009	
* Workshop Publications			
W13	A Memory Model for Multicore OCaml Stephen Dolan and KC Sivaramakrishnan OCaml Workshop	Sep 2017	
W12	Effectively Tackling the Awkward Squad Stephen Dolan, Spiros Eliopolous, Daniel Hillerstrm, Anil Madhavapeddy, KC Sivaramakrishnan, Leo White OCaml Workshop	Sep 2017	
W11	Mergeable Types Gowtham Kaki, KC Sivaramakrishnan, Samodya Abeysiriwardane, Suresh Jagannathan ML Workshop	Sep 2017	
W10	Concurrent System Programming with Effect Handlers Stephen Dolan, Spiros Eliopolous, Daniel Hillerstrm, Anil Madhavapeddy, KC Sivaramakrishnan, Leo White Symposium on Trends in Functional Programming (TFP)	Jun 2017	
W9	Eff directly in OCaml Oleg Kiselyov and KC Sivaramakrishnan JSSST Workshop on Programming and Programming Languages	Mar 2017	
W8	Lock-free programming for the masses KC Sivaramakrishnan, Tho Laurent OCaml Workshop	Sep 2016	
W7	Compiling Links Effect Handlers to the OCaml Backend Daniel Hillestrm, Sam Lindley, KC Sivaramakrishnan ML Worshop	Sep 2016	
W6	Eff Directly in OCaml Oleg Kiselyov and KC Sivaramakrishnan ML Workshop	Sep 2016	
W5	Effective Concurrency with Algebraic Effects Stephen Dolan, Leo White, KC Sivaramakrishnan, Jeremy Yallop and Anil Madhavapeddy OCaml Workshop	Sep 2015	

W4	Migrating MultiMLton to the Cloud KC Sivaramakrishnan, Lukasz Ziarek, Suresh Jagannathan ML Workshop	Sep 2013		
W3	Scalable Lightweight Task Management Schemes for MIMD Processors Daniel G. Waddington, Chen Tian, KC Sivaramakrishnan Workshop on Systems for Future Multi-Core Architectures (SFMA)	Apr 2011		
W2	The Design Rationale for MultiMLton Suresh Jagannathan, Armand Navabi, KC Sivaramakrishnan, Lukasz Ziarek ML Workshop	Sep 2010		
W1	Lightweight Asynchrony using Parasitic Threads KC Sivaramakrishnan, Lukasz Ziarek, Raghavendra Prasad, Suresh Jagannathan Workshop on Declarative Aspects of Multicore Programming (DAMP)	Jan 2010		
*	❖ Technical Reports and Drafts			

Nov 2011

Teaching/Advising

• Guest Lectures:

T1

- Arrows, Advanced Functional Programming, University of Cambridge, Lent '16.
- Debugging, Programming in C and C++, University of Cambridge, Michelmas '15.
- Supervisions at University of Cambridge:

Featherweight Threads for Communication

KC Sivaramakrishnan, Lukasz Ziarek, Suresh Jagannathan Purdue University Computer Science Technical Report – TR-11-018

- Databases, Lent '17, Michaelmas '17, Lent '16.
- Concurrent and Distributed Systems, Lent '17, Michaelmas '17, Lent '16, Michaelmas '16, Lent '15.
- Algorithms, Lent '15.
- Object-oriented Programming, Michaelmas 2015–16.
- Teaching assistantships at Purdue University
 - Undergraduate C Programming (CS180), Aug 2012 Dec 2012.
 - Graduate Programming Languages (CS565), Aug 2011 Dec 2011.
- Projects supervised:
 - Matevz Polijanc, University of Cambridge, A Reactive Programming model in OCaml, Oct 2017 Present.
 - Charlie Crisp, University of Cambridge, A Blockchain in Pure OCaml, Oct 2017 Present.
 - Henry Mercer, University of Cambridge, Systematic Concurrency Testing for Multicore OCaml, Oct 2017 Present.
 - Nicolas Assouad, ENS Paris, Hardware Support for Composable Lock-free Transactions, Mar 2017 Jun 2017.
 - Matt Harrison, University of Cambridge, Secure Decentralized Apps, Sep 2016 present.
 - Maxime Lesourd, ENS de Lyon, Verified CPS translation of handlers, Sep 2016 Mar 2017.
 - Philip Dexter, Binghampton University, Approximate computing for OCaml, May 2016 Aug 2016.
 - James Wright, University of Cambridge, Mechanized semantics of Algebraic Effects in OCaml, Sep 2015 Mar 2016.
 - Armael Gueneau, ENS de Lyon, Algebraic Effects for js_of_ocaml, Sep 2015 Mar 2016.
 - Theo Laurent, ENS, Reagents for Multicore OCaml, May 2015 Aug 2015.
 - Guillain Potron, ENS de Lyon, Semantics of Irmin branch-consistent data store, March 2015 Aug 2015.

Talks

Jul 2017 A deep dive into Multicore OCaml Garbage Collector System Research Group Seminar Computer Laboratory, University of Cambridge **Multicore OCaml GC** Jun 2017 JaneStreet Group New York, NYC Composable lock-free programming for Multicore OCaml Nov 2016 **ABCD** Meeting University of Edinburgh Practical Algebraic Effect Handlers in Multicore OCaml Nov 2016 LFCS Seminar University of Edinburgh Effective Concurrency and Parallelism in Multicore OCaml Nov 2016 PL Seminar Indian Institute of Technology, Madras **Effective Concurrency and Parallelism in Multicore OCaml** Nov 2016 PL Seminar Indian Institute of Technology, Bombay **Effective parallelism with Reagents** Sep 2016 Facebook Faculty Summit London, UK Multicore OCaml and Programming with Reagents Aug 2016 LDN Functionals Jane Street UK, London Effect handlers in Multicore OCaml Mar 2016 Dagstuhl Seminar Dagstuhl, Germany **Arrows and Reagents** Mar 2016 Invited Lecture, Advanced Functional Programming Cambridge, UK Concurrent and Multicore OCaml: A deep dive Jan 2016 Facebook Tech Talk Menlo Park, CA OCaml Platform: Update Nov 2015 OCaml Consortium Meeting Paris, France Multicore OCaml: Update Nov 2015 OCaml Developer's Meeting Paris, France Silence is Golden: Controlling Communication and Coordination in Distributed Databases Oct 2015 Darwin College Science Seminar Cambridge, UK **Effective Concurrency with Algebraic Effects** Sep 2015 OCaml Workshop 2015 Vancouver, Canada Quelea: Declarative Programming over Eventually Consistent Data Stores Apr 2015 Computer Laboratory, University of Cambridge Cambridge, UK **Functional Programming Abstractions for Weakly Consistent Systems** Dec 2014 PhD Defense Purdue University Functional Abstractions for Practical and Scalable Concurrent Programming Mar 2014 Invited Lecture Microsoft Research, Cambridge, UK Rx-CML: A Prescription for Safely Relaxing Synchrony Jan 2014 PADL 2014 San Diego, CA Migrating MultiMLton to the Cloud Sep 2013 ML Workshop 2013 Boston, MA A Coherent and Managed Runtime for ML on the SCC Nov 2012 MARC 2012 **RWTH Aachen**

Eliminating Read Barriers through Procrastination and Cleanliness

ISMM 2012, Beijing Wrestling Wednesdays, Microsoft Research, Cambridge

Lightweight Concurrency in GHC

Wrestling Wednesdays

May 2012

Microsoft Research, Cambridge

Jun 2012

CWI Amsterdam

Jun 2012

May 2012

Efficient Session Type guided Distributed Interaction COORDINATION 2012

COORDINATION 2012

Service

- Organizer, Dagstuhl Seminar on "Algebraic Effect Handlers go Mainstream", Apr 2018.
- Program Committee member: PMLDC@ECOOP 2017, Off-the-beaten track (OBT) 2017, OCaml Workshop 2016, SPLASH-MARC symposium, 2013.
- Artifact Evaluation Committee member: PLDI 2015, PPoPP/CGO 2016.
- Reviewer: ECOOP, TODS, JFP, POPL, ICFP, ASPLOS, TLDI, Concurrency and Computation: Practice and Experience, Software: Practice and Experience.
- Organizer for Darwin College Science Seminar Series, Oct 2015 May 2017.

Awards and Recognitions

- Research Fellowship, Royal Commission for the Exhibition of 1851, 2015–2018, £102,000.
- Research Fellowship, Darwin College, Cambridge, 2015–2018, £900.
- Maurice H. Halstead Memorial Award for outstanding research in Software Engineering, Purdue University, 2014, \$4,000.
- Best paper award at Many-core Architecture Research Symposium at RWTH-Aachen, 2012, \$1,000.
- Invited paper in Science of Computer Programming, Vol. 78, Iss. 2 (Feb 2013).
- Glasgow Haskell Compiler (GHC) Committer.
- SIGPLAN PAC travel grant for PLDI 2012 and POPL 2014, \$1,500 each.
- NSF travel grant for ICFP 2013, \$2,000.